<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Method on . local author .</title>
    <link>/categories/method/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Method on . local author .</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/method/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notetaking: What are you after?</title>
      <link>/posts/notetaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/notetaking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why do you want to take notes in the first place?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each person&amp;rsquo;s notetaking practice is&amp;mdash;and must be&amp;mdash;distinct. No two people have the same needs when it comes to making, organizing, and accessing notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adopting someone else&amp;rsquo;s practice just because they can loudly sing its merits, or even clearly demonstrate its efficacy, may very well be an exercise in shortsightedness. A person&amp;rsquo;s notetaking practice could certainly have merits and be effective&amp;mdash;&lt;em&gt;for them&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;but there can be no guarantee of universality in such things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, a few questions to consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why do you want (or need) to take notes at all?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What kind of information are you trying to store and keep track of?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When and how do you want to come across the stored information again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the notes be an end in themselves or raw materials for other writings?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own answers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I take notes for the purposes of academic research and lecturing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I store and keep track of the thoughts, ideas, and insights of others, as encountered in books, articles, presentations, etc., as well as my own thoughts, ideas, and insights, as they occur to me, most often in response to the thoughts (etc.) of others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to come across the stored information both as I am writing other notes, for the purposes of making connections between ideas and insights, and as I am writing research papers and lectures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My notes are both an end in themselves, to the extent that they facilitate and constitute my thinking, and raw materials for other writings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-starting-points&#34;&gt;My Starting Points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-inbox-note&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Inbox&amp;rdquo; Note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep a note that I call an &amp;ldquo;inbox&amp;rdquo; note, which is just a plaintext file on my computer. It is one of two entry-points to my notetaking pactice. When I have an idea that I want to keep track of, instead of making a new note right away (a new file on my computer), I go to my &amp;ldquo;inbox&amp;rdquo; and start writing things down, a bit freeform, right at the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider this space like a sketch pad. There is no pressure to produce anything polished or fully thought through. If I end up writing something worth keeping, I copy it into a new note (that is, a new text file&amp;mdash;each of my notes is a separate text file, all stored in a folder called &amp;ldquo;Notes&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the idea doesn&amp;rsquo;t really develop or seem worth keeping, I either delete it, or just leave it there. I will write the next idea above it, and it will simply be pushed down a few lines. The bottom of my inbox is something of a graveyard of ideas. Sometimes I go through and clean them out, to &amp;ldquo;clear the inbox,&amp;rdquo; as it were. Sometimes when I do this I find something worth recovering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the &amp;ldquo;inbox&amp;rdquo; note is to eliminate any friction that might disrupt the actual taking of a note when the need/desire to take a note arises. It allows me to get right to the important business of putting an idea down and avoid having to fool with any other, less pressing business, like finding the right place to put the idea. I have a shortcut key that opens the inbox note right away. Highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-literature-note&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Literature&amp;rdquo; Note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often I am taking notes on something I&amp;rsquo;m reading, be it a book, an article, or a website. After entering the appropriate citation information into my bibliographic database and assigning the resource a unique &lt;a href=&#34;../posts/citekeys.html&#34;&gt;citekey&lt;/a&gt;, I skip the &amp;ldquo;inbox&amp;rdquo; and go straight to creating a new note dedicated to the material I am reading. This is called a literature note.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of each literature note is the resource&amp;rsquo;s unique citekey followed by its author and title, like so: &amp;ldquo;Conrad1899 - Joseph Conrad - Heart of Darkness.txt&amp;rdquo;. By having a programmatic titling scheme, I always know right where to find my notes for what I&amp;rsquo;ve read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read, I keep the literature note open and write down ideas, quotations, and questions as they occur to me, always making reference to the appropriate page number when relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any idea or line of thought arises while reading that seems interesting enough to stand on its own, I can make a separate note for it, and include a reference to that new note in the literature note itself. A literature note could be a page-by-page account of a resource, or it could be a list of references to stand-alone notes. Most often it is somewhere in between.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See Sönke Ahrens, &lt;i&gt;How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking&lt;/i&gt; (North Charleston, SC: CreateSpace, 2017).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The matter of inserting references to other notes can be facilitated by any number of progams. I use a package I wrote for Emacs called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/localauthor/zk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;zk&lt;/a&gt;, demonstrations of which can be seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BixlUK4QTNk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7qNT87dphiA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O6iSV4pQQ5g&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Similar programs worth looking at are &lt;a href=&#34;https://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;nvALT&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://zettelkasten.de/the-archive&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Archive&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://zettlr.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Zettlr&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citekeys: For Better Research / Life</title>
      <link>/posts/citekeys/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 23:19:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/citekeys/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;citekeys&lt;/strong&gt; to consistently and uniformly correlate in-text references
with original source materials, not just in final submissions but &lt;strong&gt;also in
notes and drafts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long research projects, it is necessary not only to keep straight a
variety of sources but also to ensure that in-text references to those
sources are unambiguous. This allows readers to trace all lines of thought to
their original contexts. This is obviously a requirement of all formal
publications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a clear and consistent citation practice should not be neglected in the
writing that leads up to a final submission, such as notes, outlines, drafts,
etc. When you are still the project&amp;rsquo;s primary (or only) reader, you must
still be able to trace lines of thought to their origins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases, this may not be difficult. In the middle of a project, when
everything is fresh in your working memory, you might be able to make sense
of all kinds of non-standard forms of citation, no matter how informal: &amp;ldquo;cite
book on national identity formation,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;quote comes from that article we read
during week 3,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;see Foucault 257.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the larger a project is and the more time that passes between note-taking
and final submission the more effort will be involved in tracing such
citations to their sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of a career researcher, informal citations like the above will
inevitably lose their meaning as their originary contexts recede into the
past. Which book on national identity formation was that? Which class? Which
book by Foucault, and &lt;em&gt;which edition&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of &lt;em&gt;citekeys&lt;/em&gt; can greatly reduce the effort involved in mainlining
clear lines of connection between citations and sources&amp;mdash;not just in final
products but in notes and drafts as well, and not just in single projects but
in a lifetime of research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;citekey-basics&#34;&gt;Citekey Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A citekey (or citation key) is a unique code assigned to a particular piece
of source material that can be used to quickly and consistently refer to that
source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A citekey is typically composed of some combination of the source&amp;rsquo;s year of
publication, its primary author&amp;rsquo;s surname, and/or a short version of its
title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are three different citekeys, in three common styles, that could be used
for the same source, the book &lt;em&gt;Imagined Communities&lt;/em&gt; by Benedict Anderson.
Each offers a far more precise indication of what source is being referred to
than the comparatively ambiguous &amp;ldquo;cite book on national identity formation&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-nil&#34; data-lang=&#34;nil&#34;&gt;Anderson2006
andersonImaginedCommunities2006
anderson2006_ImaginedCommunities
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that citekeys are not expected to be clearly
understandable to anyone other than the researcher who assigns them.
Consider that &amp;ldquo;Anderson2006&amp;rdquo; in the example above could refer to any number
of publications from the year 2006 by anyone with the surname Anderson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way citekeys are unlike ISBN or DOI numbers: they are not universal
indicators&amp;mdash;they do not point directly and unambiguously to particular
sources themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather, citekeys point to a researcher&amp;rsquo;s own individual collection of
bibliographic entries (more on this ahead). Citekeys offer, as a result, a
simple, private system of shorthand for encoding reference information into
any written document, all without the work entailed in writing out full
formal citations and bibliographic entries in every instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given their simplicity and ease of use, citekeys help to lower any barriers
that might otherwise have impeded the inclusion of clear, reliable citations
in even the most informal of written documents, including and especially
those that are not intended for publication. They thereby help to eliminate
any temptation to insert ambiguous and cryptic notes-to-self that risk
baffling more than benefiting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-bibliographic-database&#34;&gt;Your Bibliographic Database&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For texts that are intended to be published, citekeys offer great
flexibility, as they can be easily replaced with formal citations in whatever
citation style is appropriate to the intended context, such as Chicago, MLA,
Harvard, APA, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This requires maintaining a centralized repository of bibliographic
information wherein all citekeys are listed with relevant information about
the associated source. This may sound more complicated than it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is possible to manage bibliographic information with one of the many
popular reference management programs&amp;mdash;such as Zotero, Endnote, or
Mandeley&amp;mdash;it is equally possible to maintain nothing more than a simple text
document of entries like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-nil&#34; data-lang=&#34;nil&#34;&gt;@book{Anderson2006,
        title = &amp;#34;Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism&amp;#34;,
        author = Anderson, Benedict&amp;#34;,
        year = &amp;#34;2006&amp;#34;,
        publisher = &amp;#34;Verso&amp;#34;,
        address = &amp;#34;London; New York&amp;#34;,
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The above entry happens to be written in a standardized format called BibTeX,
often used or at least supported by reference management software. For the
sake of future-proofing your bibliography, it might be worthwhile to use such
a standardized format.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But such entries can easily be written and maintained in any format and
without such software, using nothing more than a plaintext editing program
like TextEdit (MacOS) or Notepad (Windows). The most important thing is to
include all the relevant information about the source and associate it with a
unique citekey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From such information, it will be possible to produce citations and
references in any of a seemingly endless array of standardized citation
styles.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-rule-be-consistent&#34;&gt;Key Rule: Be Consistent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what style of citekey or method of bibliography management is used,
internal consistency is essential. Use a consistent citekey style&amp;mdash;I use
AuthorYEAR, like &amp;ldquo;Anderson2006&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;so that each source is associated with a
only single citekey. Do not use both &amp;ldquo;Anderson2006&amp;rdquo; and
&amp;ldquo;andersonImaginedCommunities2006.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, take care to ensure that each citekey is associated with only a single
source. If you add a source by a different Anderson also written in 2006,
assign it a unique citekey, like &amp;ldquo;Anderson2006a&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Anderson2006-1.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that using citekeys also makes it easy to include and distinguish
between different editions of a single text. You might also have reason to
cite the first edition of &lt;em&gt;Imagined Communities&lt;/em&gt; (1983) alongside the
reprint. Luckily, there is no confusing &amp;ldquo;Anderson1983&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Anderson2006.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;citekeys-in-use&#34;&gt;Citekeys In Use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing a citekey style, assigning citekeys to sources, and keeping them all
matched up in a bibliography database is only the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve done all that, how to go about putting them to use in your
writings?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example from my reading notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heise cites [#Anderson2006], who make a similar connection between representations and identity-formation.[5][#Heise2008]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not taking these notes for any specific project or a potential
publication where accurate citations would be necessary. Nevertheless, it was
so simple to include the citekeys and a page reference that I didn&amp;rsquo;t consider
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the use of citekeys, formatted in a distinct syntax&amp;mdash;in brackets,
preceed by the hash sign&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;mdash;that made it effortless to find this
reference (along with several others) to Anderson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Imagined Communities&lt;/em&gt; in
a file on my computer that is not obviously about the text in question and
that I haven&amp;rsquo;t looked at or thought about since I wrote it. How about that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-pdf-management&#34;&gt;Bonus: PDF Management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from helping you keep your citations legible and locate deeply embedded
notes in the recesses of your file system, citekeys can also help you keep
track of PDFs and other digital documents. No longer worry over what to name
that PDF. Enter its information into your bibliography file, assign it a
citekey, and use the citekey as the name of the file. You&amp;rsquo;ll never have to
guess what &amp;ldquo;Anderson2006.pdf&amp;rdquo; contains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibtex.com/g/bibtex-format/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.bibtex.com/g/bibtex-format/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://citationstyles.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://citationstyles.org&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These citations are in a syntax called &lt;a href=&#34;https://fletcher.github.io/MultiMarkdown-5/citations.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MultiMarkdown&lt;/a&gt;. A similar syntax, called &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org/MANUAL.html#citation-syntax&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, uses the &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; prefix instead of the &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;, among other differences: [@Anderson2006, p 22-23].&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drafting, Beyond MS Word</title>
      <link>/posts/drafting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 12:56:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/drafting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no good way to write an essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; several bad ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too common, I think, is the impulse
to open up a fresh document in Microsoft Word
&amp;mdash; or Google Docs, or LibreOffice&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&amp;mdash; and begin banging away at whatever process has worked in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That process &amp;mdash; whether it be freewriting, or transcribing, or listing, or outlining
&amp;mdash; &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be effective, or it might not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;em&gt;forum&lt;/em&gt; in which that process takes place all-too-often
&amp;mdash; the blank white simulated piece of paper
&amp;mdash; is &lt;em&gt;certainly&lt;/em&gt; not doing you any favors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once saw the great Ted Nelson&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; give a talk (screed)
in a library, in which he denounced (railed against)
the usage of the term &amp;ldquo;desktop&amp;rdquo; in personal computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many desktops, he asked (shouted), are positioned &lt;em&gt;vertically&lt;/em&gt;
in front of you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly: do you really need to type out your essay&amp;rsquo;s fledgling stages
on something that &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like a piece of paper&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; just because that&amp;rsquo;s the particular physicality that your essay will take on &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest, though &amp;mdash; your essay will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; take on the physicality of a piece of paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because you&amp;rsquo;re not going to print your essay out on paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re just going to email it to someone, who is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; not going to print it out on paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, what else can you do? Where else can you write?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do me a favor:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open TextEdit (on MacOS) or Notepad (on Windows).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start your essay-writing process, whatever that might entail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does it feel to be writing in a space ungoverned
by the arbitrary geometries of the US Letter or A4 sheet?&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you feel liberated? No? Well, give it a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve enabled &amp;ldquo;Word Wrap&amp;rdquo; (Notepad) or &amp;ldquo;Wrap to Page&amp;rdquo; (TextEdit) try resizing
the window so you can only see the few sentences you&amp;rsquo;re working on.
How does that feel?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liberating? No? &lt;em&gt;Then try something else.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The point here is not to prescribe a way of writing
but rather to prompt the shaking loose of the notion of prescription.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no straight line through the production of an essay
and, accordingly, no good reason why a process as messy and full of switchbacks as writing
tends to be should take place on the image of a facsimile of a white piece paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, you can always paste your draft into Word later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A free and open-source (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%5Fand%5Fopen-source%5Fsoftware&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;FOSS&lt;/a&gt;) alternative to MS Word: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.libreoffice.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.libreoffice.org/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted%5FNelson&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted_Nelson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeuomorph#Virtual%5Fexamples&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeuomorph#Virtual_examples&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do yourself a favor.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paper%5Fsize&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paper_size&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Textual Encounters of the Worthwhile Kind</title>
      <link>/posts/textual-encounters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 22:07:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/textual-encounters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reading without taking notes is as good as not reading at all.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of the last text you read &amp;mdash; a book, a chapter, an article, a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you remember about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;verse&#34;&gt;
What do you remember more clearly:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;a) The text itself.&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;b) The circumstances in which you read it.&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;c) The feeling of accomplishment that came over you when you finished reading.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I, for one, do not remember the last book I read. (Or the last article, chapter, or blog post.)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe I remember a title, a general topic, an author&amp;rsquo;s name &amp;mdash; sometimes more.&lt;br /&gt;
But that one anecdote on such-and-such a page? The footnote with all the citations that seemed so promising? The statement of argument a third of the way through the introduction?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re gone. Like they never existed. And like we, therefore, never encountered each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; encounter each other&amp;hellip;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what was it all &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I am reading something that I find to be of significant moment &amp;mdash; something compelling, inciting, &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; I make a text file on my computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that file, I take notes on whatever strikes me about what I am reading. Beside each note, I write a page number. It ends up looking something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[40]: Crusoe arrives on the island.&lt;br /&gt;
[72]: RC can&amp;rsquo;t believe there&amp;rsquo;s corn growing.&lt;br /&gt;
[75]: Can we consider this an immaculate corn-ception?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I type direct quotes from the text. But often I only describe, in a few words, what is being discussed on a given page: analysis of a primary or secondary source, discussion of a concept, definition of a key term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later when I need to recall some details about something I&amp;rsquo;ve read, I&amp;rsquo;ve got a clear and easily accessible record of my reading.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this process distinct, noteworthy, worthy of note? The following precept, which I try as hard as possible to adhere to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do not make any notes in the text itself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s right. No underlining, no highlighting, no notes in the margins.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not in the interest of keeping a clean original document, digital or otherwise.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No &amp;mdash; it is to prevent me from &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt; like some work has been done when, in reality, &lt;em&gt;no work&lt;/em&gt; has been done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underlining and highlighting &lt;em&gt;feel great&lt;/em&gt;. They are easy. They feel like an accomplishment. But once you close a book or pdf, what do you have? Quickly fading memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, you have books and pdfs full of marks. But to get to those marks, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to go back to the books/pdfs themselves &amp;mdash; if you can find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, what do those marks really &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll have to read the underlined/highlighted portions of text &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; in order to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt;, if you&amp;rsquo;re like me &amp;mdash; and I assume you are &amp;mdash; you will wonder half the time why you thought a passage was worth underlining/highlighting in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.org-center { margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of extra work later when you can do a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; extra work now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the answer to this question, of course. It&amp;rsquo;s because you&amp;rsquo;re the &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; you, and you don&amp;rsquo;t care about the &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt; you, and all the work that they may or may not have to do. Let &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re going to be &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; mad&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where do I keep these notes? What kind of files are they? How do I title them? How do I search through them? What if I want to refer to another note? Or to another text? Questions, questions&amp;hellip;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
